上一节里我们看了两个主动攻击
In the last segment, we saw two active
attacks that can completely destroy the
它们可以完全破坏CPA安全加密的安全性。
本节我们将定义一个新概念
security of CPA secure encryption. In this
segment, we're gonna define a new concept,
叫做认证加密，即存在主动攻击者也能保持安全
called authenticated encryption, that
remains secure in the presence of an
后面几节里，我们将组建加密机制
active adversary. In later segments, we'll
construct encryption schemes that satisfy
来满足认证加密这一概念。那认证加密是什么？
this new authenticated encryption concept.
So what is authenticated encryption?
认证加密是一个密码，通常是个加密算法
Authenticated encryption is a cipher where
as usual the encryption algorithm takes a
取密钥、信息为输入，还可选一个新鲜值，输出一个密文
key, a message and optionally a nonce and outputs
a cipher text. The decryption algorithm as
解密算法通常通常输出一个信息。但是
这个解密算法可以输出一个特殊符号
usual outputs a message. However, here the
decryption algorithm is allowed to output
叫做底⊥。当解密算法输出符号⊥时
a special symbol called bottom. When the
decryption algorithm outputs the symbol
意味着密文是无效的，应当被忽略
bottom, basically it says that the cipher
text is invalid and should be ignored. The
唯一的要求是这个⊥不在信息空间里
only requirement is that this bottom is
not in the message space so that in fact
事实上⊥是一个唯一的符号，表示密文应当被拒绝
it is a unique symbol that indicates that
the cipher text should be rejected. Now
现在一个认证加密系统是安全的是什么意思？
what does it mean for an authenticated
encryption system to be secure? Well the
这个系统必须满足两个性质。第一个性质是
system has to satisfy two properties. The
first property is that it has to be
它必须像之前一样对选择明文攻击是语义安全的
semantically secure under a chosen
plaintext attack just as before. But now
第二个性质是，这个系统必须满足密文完整性
there's a second property which says that
the system also has to satisfy what's
这意味着尽管攻击者
called cipher text integrity. What that
means is that even though the attacker
能看到许多密文，他也不应该能阐述
gets to see a number of cipher texts, it
should not be able to produce another
另外一个能顺利解密的密文。换句话说
cipher text that decrypts properly. In
other words, that decrypts to something
能被解密成其他东西，而不是符号⊥。
更精确地，我们看这个密文完整性游戏
other than bottom. More precisely,
let's look at the ciphertext integrity game.
这里(E,D)是一个信息空间M上的密码。
通常，挑战者开始时
So here, (E,D) is a cipher with message
space M. As usual, the challenger begins
选择一个随机密钥K。攻击者可以提交他选择的信息
by choosing a random key K. And
the adversary can submit messages of his
收到这些信息的加密
choice, and receive the encryptions of
those messages. So here, C1 is the
这里C1是M1的加密，M1由攻击者选择
encryption of M1, where M1 was chosen by
the adversary. And the adversary can do
攻击者可以反复这样操作。换句话说，攻击者
提交M2，并获得M2的加密结果
this repeatedly. In other words, he
submits M2 and obtains the encryption of
等等。。他提交许多信息，直到Mq
M2, and so on and so forth. He submits
many more messages up until Mq and obtains
并获得了所有这些信息的加密结果。
那么这里攻击者获得了q个密文
the encryption of all those messages. So
here the adversary obtained Q cipher texts
都是他选择的信息的密文。然后他的目标是
产生某个新的有效密文
for messages of his choice. Then his goal
is to produce some new cipher text that's
我们说攻击者赢得了游戏，如果这个攻击者产生的
valid. So we'll say that the adversary
wins the game if basically this new cipher
新密文被正确地解密了。换句话说
text that the adversary created decrypts
correctly, in other words decrypts to
被解密成了不是符号⊥的东西。它是某个新密文
something other than bottom. And it's a
new cipher text. In other words, it's not
换句话说，它不是选择明文攻击中给攻击者的密文之一
one of the cipher texts that was given to
the adversary as part of this chosen
然后通常我们定义在这个密文完整性游戏中
plaintext attack. And then as usual we
defined the adversary's advantage in the
攻击者的优势为挑战者在游戏最后输出1的概率
cipher text integrity game as the
probability that the challenger outputs
我们说这个密码有密文完整性
one at the end of the game and we'll say
that the cipher has cipher text integrity
如果事实上对所有的有效攻击者，其赢得游戏的优势
if in fact for all efficient adversaries
the advantage in winning this game is
都是可忽略的。现在我们理解了密文完整性
negligible. So now that we understand
what cipher text integrity is. We can
我们可以定义认证加密了。我们说
define authenticated encryption and
basically we say that the cipher has
密码有认证加密，如果像我们说的，对于选择明文攻击
authenticated encryption if as we said
it's semantically secure under a chosen
它是语义安全的，并且它还有密文完整性
plaintext attack and it also has cipher
text integrity. So just as a bad example,
作为一个反面教材，带随机IV的CBC不提供认证加密
let me mention that CBC with a random IV
does not provide authenticated encryption
因为对于攻击者来说，很容易赢得密文完整性游戏
because it's very easy for the adversary
to win the cipher text integrity game.
攻击者提交一个随机密文
The adversary simply submits a random cipher text
由于CBC的解密算法从不输出符号⊥
and since the decryption algorithm for
CBC encryption never outputs bottom,
他总是输出某些信息，攻击者轻松获得游戏胜利
it always outputs some message,
the adversary just easily wins the game.
任何奇怪的随机密文都会被解密成某些不是符号⊥的东西
Any odd random cipher text will decrypt
to something other than bottom
因此攻击者直接取得密文完整性游戏的胜利
and therefore the adversary directly wins
the cipher-text integrity game. So this is just
这是个简单例子，CPA安全的密码并不提供认证加密
a trivial example of a CPA secure cipher that
does not provide authenticated encryption.
我想提一下认证加密的两个影响
So I wanna mention two implications of
authenticated encryption. The first I'll
首先我称之为认证，意味着攻击者无法欺骗接收方Bob
call authenticity, which means that,
basically, an attacker cannot fool the
让Bob认为Alice发送了一条实际上她没有发过的信息
recipient, Bob, into thinking that Alice
sent a certain message that she didn't
我们看这是什么意思。这里
actually send. So let's see what I mean by
that. Well, here, the attacker basically
攻击者与Alice互动，让她去加密任意他选择的信息
gets to interact with Alice, and get her
to encrypt arbitrary messages of his
这是一个选择明文攻击。然后攻击者的目标是
choice. So this is a chosen plain text
attack. And then the attacker's goal is to
产生某些不是由Alice创造的密文
produce some cipher text that was not
actually created by Alice. And because the
因为攻击者不能赢下这个密文完整性游戏，他不能做到
attacker can't win the cipher text
integrity game, he can't do this. What
意味着当Bob接收能被解密算法正确解密的密文时
this means is, when Bob receives the
cipher text that decrypts correctly under
他知道信息一定来自某知道密钥K的人
the decryption algorithm, he knows that
the message must have come from someone
特别地，如果Alice是唯一知道K的人
who knows the secret key K. In particular,
if Alice is the only one who knows K, then
那么他知道密文确实是来自Alice
he knows the cipher text really did come
from Alice, and it's not some modification
并非攻击者发出的某些修改。现在唯一剩下的警告是
that was sent by the attacker. Now the
only caveat to that is that authenticated
认证加密无法抵抗重放攻击。特别地
encryption doesn't defend against replay
attacks. In particular, the attacker
攻击者可以截获某些从Alice到Bob的密文
could've intercepted some cipher text from
Alice to Bob. And could have replayed it
攻击者可以重放信息，这样重放的密文对Bob来说
看起来也是有效的。例如
and both cipher text would look valid to
Bob. So for example, Alice might send a
Alice可能向Bob发送了条信息，说转100美元给Charlie
message to Bob saying transfer $100 to
Charlie. Then Charlie could replay that
那么Charlie可以重放这条密文，这样
Bob会再转100美元给Charlie
cipher text and as a result, Bob would
transfer another $100 to Charlie. So in
所以事实上，任何加密协议必须能防御重放攻击
fact, any encryption protocol has to
defend against replay attacks and this is
但这是认证算法能直接阻止得了的
not something that's directly prevented by
authenticated encryption. And we'll come
下面两节，我们会回来并讨论重放攻击。
第二个认证加密的影响在于
back and talk about replay attacks in two
segments. The second implication of
它能抵抗一种非常强力的攻击者
authenticated encryption is that it
defends against a very powerful type of
即能实施所谓选择密文攻击
adversary, namely an adversary that can
mount what's called a chosen cipher text
我们下节讨论它
attack. We're going to talk about that
actually in the next segment.